A Guide to the Mr. and Mrs. James Hoover Collection of Strickler Family Papers, 1776-1963: SC 0098
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Mr. and Mrs. James Hoover Collection of Strickler Family Papers,
1776-1963
Special Collections, James Madison University
Hoover, Anna B., 1937-2008
Hoover, James B., 1934-
Strickler Family
SC 0098
1 Cubic Feet; 2 Hollinger boxes, 1 oversize folder
This collection deals mainly with the Strickler family of Massanutten, Egypt Bend, and Luray, Virginia, along with a few other related families.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Carrier Library by Mrs. James Hoover of Harrisonburg in May 1993.
Bio/Historical Note
Abraham Strickler was one of the original settlers of the Shenandoah Valley at Massanutten (now Page County) in the 1720s. He was born in Zurich, Switzerland. He first settled in America around 1700 in the province of Pennsylvania. He then migrated to Virginia and settled about 4 miles west of Luray. His descendants figured prominently in the life of the region. Abraham is credited as being the ancestor of most of the Stricklers in Shenandoah County.
Scope and Content
The Mr. and Mrs. James Hoover Collection of Strickler Family Papers, 1776-1963, consists of two Hollinger boxes and a few oversize materials dealing largely with the Strickler family of Massanutten, Egypt Bend, and Luray, in what would become Page County, Virginia in 1831, and a few related families. There are scattered documents relevant to related families, especially the Civil War correspondence of the Kauffmans, but the bulk of the collection documents parts of the lives of two Mary Stricklers (1860s, 1907-1940s); Joseph and Joseph T. Strickler (1810-1856, 1890s); and Baptist Elder Reuben T. Strickler (1881-1903). There is also some correspondence concerning the Strickler land claim and experiences in Oregon and Washington Territory (1860s-1880s).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Letters & Genealogy, 1776-1963
Business & Legal Documents, 1810-1928
Miscellaneous, 1865-1904
Oversize, 1818-1889
Related Material
L. R. Milbourne Papers, 1886 - 1906, SC 0108, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va. L. R. Milbourne Papers, 1886 - 1906, SC 0108, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
Hoover, Anna B., 1937-2008; Hoover, James B., 1934-
- Series 1: Letters and Genealogy, 1776-1963
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1835-1860, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    From surnames Coffman, Ward, Crim, & others, mostly to Strickler family in Luray; mention of land purchases in the Valley, typhoid fever, farm & financial news. A few from Oregon concern prospecting in Rogue River. Includes an autograph copy of a letter from A. Strickler at University of VA to Dr. Thomas (Dec. 10, 1835).
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Mostly between Robert G. Mauck in Page Cty & nephews Joseph F. & E.V. Kauffman & brother John W. Mauck, all in the 10th VA Reg., who wrote from various camps of camp life & troop movements. R. Mauck writes of farm news and "excitement and rumors of all kinds" (June 24, 1861)
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1863-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Several from E.V. Kauffman from camp. Most of rest are to Mary Strickler from grandson Will concerning death in family. Mention of Cambellites (Sept. 1, 1866).
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1867-1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Mostly to Mary Strickler at Massanutten, including from grandson Will in Washington D.C. Details of W.A. Strickler's land claim in Washington Territory and his disappearance.
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1870-1878 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Friends & Strickler family in VA, WV, OH, NV, IL, MO, KS; two items related to Mill Creek Church (1874, 1879).
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1880-1882 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Mostly from W.S. Strickler in NV, where he was working, prospecting & mining, to brother Reuben T. & other relatives in VA.
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1883-1886, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Mostly from W.S. & J.G. Strickler in NV & Dakota to relatives in Page Cty; a few from Joshua Ruffner in ID & MT to VA. Several items related to Mill Creek Church.
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1887-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Mostly to Reuben T. Strickler from relatives & Baptist Church members.
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1907-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Mostly from family & friends with news of home to Mary Strickler, in Page County & later in Washington, D.C. One of Mary's school compositions (1913?) mentions gypsies in Page Cty. Some items incomplete.
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1919-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Con't previous file; includes documents related to Mary Strickler's husband S.B. (Beery) Hoover; letters to Litha Strickler. Genealogy, 1770s
  - Letters and Genealogy, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Business Legal Documents, 1810-1928; Series 2
  - Business Receipts, 1810-1928 (bulk 1890); bulk 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Property tax receipts of Jos. Strickler, 1810-1827; property tax receipts of Mary Rooff (adm. Jos. Strickler), 1810-1832; 1813 birth verification of Negro girl; inventory of Jos. Strickler estate, 1856; inventories & receipts for estate of Jos. T. Strickler, 1890 (see also Oversize); misc. other items.
  - Seven Railroad timetables, 1880s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes Shenandoah Valley Route and several other Virginia routes.
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    District of Jos. Strickler, Commissioner of Revenue for Shenandoah Cty, 1815 (see also Oversize), '17, '19, '21, '22, '23, '26 (?, with list of licenses issued), '27, & und.
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lists of land and property taxes, 1815-1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ledgers, 1821-1826 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Debt/interest ledger (?), Jos. Strickler (?),; bound with store/labor ledger, Jos. & Jos. T. Strickler (?), 1835-1864. See also oversize.
- Miscellaneous, 1865-1904; Series 3
  - Miscellaneous, 1865-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes religious pamphlet by J.G. Strickler (2 cop.), Minutes of Ebenezer Baptist Assoc. sessions (65,68,69,76, 1893-1904), Luray & Bridgewater newsletters (1885-93), & unidentified printed German poem.
- Oversize, 1818-1889; Series 4
  - Oversize, 1818-1889 (Box OV, Folder 1)
    Store/labor ledger, John Mauk (?), 1818-25; unknown, 1866-1889. List of property taxes, 1815. Broadside advertising estate sale of J.T. Strickler, 1889.